This video is sponsored by the gamified
software development platform boot.dev.
Stick around for the sponsored segment
at the end of the video to receive a
unique discount that isn't in the
description.
There's a theory in physics that, when
followed to its conclusion, something
very strange happens. The entire
universe seems to open up like a cosmic
accordion. One world becomes many.
The future sort of becomes everything.
The weirdest part is what it implies for
you,
about you.
According to this particular idea, you
will never experience your own death.
Not because upon your death you will no
longer be around to experience [music]
anything,
but because you will never actually die.
When physicists attempt to make sense of
the theory known as quantum mechanics,
which deals with the fundamental
particles that make up reality, there
seems to be a kind of immortality that
emerges. This immortality is not the
kind we typically think of.
It's not heaven or hell, not eternal
youth, not technological augmentation,
not legacy.
Rather, it is a kind of probabilistic
continuance of your awareness forever.
The idea is known as quantum
immortality.
Despite the seemingly absurd proposition
of this, and despite the highly
contentious arguments around it, the
idea has become increasingly popular
over the last few decades and has been
seriously explored by leading physicists
and philosophers.
In the last couple of years, it's also
become increasingly popular in various
pockets of the internet. Naturally,
there's a lot of misunderstanding,
misrepresentation, and divergence
[music] in discussions around it. And of
course, there's no real consensus.
In large part, that's primarily because
it's seemingly unfalsifiable. It's
simply a highly speculative
philosophical exploration of one
interpretation of quantum mechanics.
But it does eerily map onto this
interpretation, which itself cleanly
fits the math of quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics is just extremely
weird in relation to our sensibilities.
In the words of physicist Niels Bohr,
"Those who are not shocked when they
first come across quantum theory cannot
possibly have understood it."
Regardless of consensus or verifiable
truth, the existential implications of
quantum immortality remain undeniable
and profound. It reveals something
extremely destabilizing [music]
about the nature of who each of us are,
or perhaps what we are in this
verifiable reality.
The teleportation thought experiment.
Consider the following thought
experiment.
>> [music]
>> It is some many years in the future.
Science and technology has since
developed a new way to travel.
>> [music]
>> You can now get to and from any
accessible destination in a matter of
moments through teleportation.
Using a global network of ports, [music]
travelers step into a dedicated
teleportation pod, and then every
particle of their body and brain is
scanned, mapped, and [music] modeled. In
an instant, each particle's position and
state are then perfectly reassembled in
the location [music] of their choosing.
You've already used this method for a
few vacations. Most people have. It's
painless, cheap, and obscenely
convenient.
Today you're about to head to Bermuda.
Like every other time, you enter the
teleportation pod and follow all the
instructions. In an instant, without
missing a beat, you arrive on the
archipelago as if nothing had happened.
As if you had simply taken a next step.
>> [music]
>> Except this time, when you look next to
you, there's a problem. During the
reconstruction phase, there was a glitch
and the system ran the model twice.
At the landing pod, now there are two of
you.
Two perfect identical copies.
Clones. Both picking up exactly from
where you left off when you were [music]
scanned.
Now in both versions, all of your
memories are the same, all your
preferences and values, all your body
parts and birthmarks.
>> [music]
>> Everything is preserved and identical.
But now there are two separate versions
of you that will go two separate ways in
the world.
Like with all transportation methods,
sometimes there are accidents. Sometimes
there are tragedies. It's unclear
exactly what this is.
After all, you survived. You didn't lose
anything. From your perspective,
everything remained the same and went
exactly as it should.
Only now it seems this way from the
perspective of two of you.
What if instead of both of you arriving
cleanly, one of you arrived normally and
the other arrived as a puddle of flesh,
liquid, and brain matter? All the
particles still there, but not
containing any life.
Did you die?
Did you live?
Which one is you?
Are both you?
Is neither you?
This isn't quantum mechanics, but it
illustrates the extremely weird and
unsettling relationship we each seem to
have with the theory.
At least one interpretation of it.
The problem of quantum mechanics.
I remember discussions with Niels Bohr,
which went through many hours till very
late at night and ended almost in
despair.
And when at the end of the discussion, I
went alone for a walk in the neighboring
park, I repeated to myself again and
again the question, [music]
"Can nature possibly be so absurd as it
seemed to us in these atomic
experiments?"
Werner Heisenberg.
At its foundation, quantum [music]
mechanics is a theory in physics about
the behavior of microscopic particles,
photons, neutrons, electrons, and so on.
Seems simple enough, but at this level,
for some unknown reason, all the
ordinary classical understandings of
physics seem to [music] break down.
Quantum mechanics attempts to make sense
of this, but in doing so, it seemingly
only reveals a dissonance between the
microscopic and macroscopic worlds.
Things are so weird down there that all
our terms, understandings, and
explanations seem to struggle to cleanly
map onto it, [music] if at all.
It's as if these particles at the
quantum level are a kind of tiny window
[music] into another realm of reality,
which we can peer into, but can't get
through.
The key issue that quantum mechanics
reveals is that these particles do not
seem to function in a deterministic way.
That is, at this most fundamental level
of reality, everything seems to be
random.
At the macro level, of course, when we
push a domino, it falls. And if there's
another domino in front of it, it hits
it, and that one falls, too. So, on and
so forth.
We press the accelerator pedal in a car,
more fuel and air are supplied to the
engine, the engine spins faster, the
wheels turn, and we accelerate forward.
We pull a trigger or flip a switch over
and over in the exact same way, with the
exact same conditions, and over and
over, the same things happen.
Everything operates through clear cause
and [music] effect. But at the quantum
level, if you push a particle, what it
does next is [music] uncertain,
apparently random.
It does different things and shows up in
different places for seemingly no clear
reason.
Through various research and
experiments,
>> [music]
>> like the famous double-slit experiment
and quantum eraser experiment, what
seems to be the case is that particles
behave more like waves, not waves of
energy, but a kind of distribution of
probability.
This is described by what is known as
the wave function, which is a
mathematical description physicists use
to describe all the possible ways a
particle could behave and their
probabilities.
The result of this is that particles are
in a state of a kind of uncertainty.
They're in what is known as
superposition, where multiple different
positions or states exist
simultaneously. But things get even
weirder. When a specific particle is
measured, its state or position suddenly
becomes defined [music] in accordance
with normal deterministic physics. The
wave function collapses.
In other words, measurements or
observations seem to [music] be almost
part of the equation itself.
The most famous demonstration of this is
through what is known as the double-slit
experiment, where researchers fire
individual particles at a barrier with
two vertical slits, without observing
which slit they pass through. This
produces a wave-like pattern on the
other side of the slits against a
backdrop wall, known as an interference
pattern, as though each particle behaved
like a wave, each moving through both
slits at the same time. But when a
detector is placed at the slits to
determine which slit each particle
passes through, suddenly the wave-like
pattern disappears [music]
and the particles behave as though they
were defined and had a single path,
creating two lines on the back wall.
When we look, particles seem to suddenly
almost play [music] along, like a Toy
Story character whose behavior decides
the literal conditions of everything.
But why does measurement or observation
change anything? And more importantly,
what constitutes a measurement or
observation?
This is what is known as the measurement
problem.
Measurement here can often be conflated
with a kind of conscious observation,
but most modern physicists think that is
likely both unnecessary [music] and
deviating from the reality. The
requirement for measurement or
interaction seems to be nothing more
than a particle simply interacting with
its environment, [music]
like an electron bumping into a photon.
But if this is true, how then is not
everything a kind of measurement?
Wouldn't the wave function just always
be collapsing?
Or to the contrary, if everything is
made of quantum particles, why wouldn't
everything always be caught in the
continuous evolution of the wave
function to begin with?
Perhaps everything [music] is.
Infinite worlds and infinite yous.
In 1957, in an effort to make sense of
and resolve the problems of quantum
mechanics, physicist Hugh Everett
offered a revolutionary interpretation.
Up until this point, prior
interpretations primarily involved
trying to map the classical world at the
macro level onto the quantum realm.
In what is known as the Copenhagen
interpretation, which was the leading
interpretation following the 1920s, the
idea was that to when a particle is
measured, the wave function collapses
and the particle goes from an
indeterminate state to suddenly a
defined one, just how it appears to us.
>> [music]
>> Everett, however, found this to be both
incomplete and disingenuous to the
reality of what is happening.
There is no part of the equation that
suggests a sudden collapse or observer
variable.
Referring to his efforts to resolve the
conflict, Everett says,
"This paper proposes to regard pure wave
mechanics [music] as a complete theory.
It postulates that a wave function that
obeys a linear wave equation everywhere
and at all times supplies a complete
mathematical model for every isolated
physical system without exception."
And so, Everett suggested we simply
follow the wave function wherever it
takes us.
Put differently, we shouldn't assume it
collapses simply because that's what our
observation suggests. Rather, we should
accept that the complete math is
complete and fully describes reality.
If we do this, however, what it suggests
is that every possible state of every
quantum particle is [music] real
simultaneously.
Of course, this raises the following
questions. If all possible states of a
particle are real and exist
simultaneously, why do we only see one
when measuring and observing them? And
why does only one outcome of the world
appear to exist?
Everett's answer is one of the strangest
ideas to be taken seriously in modern
science,
the many worlds interpretation.
According to the many worlds
interpretation, this conflict is
essentially a consequence of our
abilities or inabilities of observation,
not a conflict in reality.
Since we as observers are also part of
the quantum world, when we interact with
or observe quantum particles, we become
entangled with the particles we measure
and thus also with the one outcome we
see.
But reality fundamentally splits into
branches at each point of interaction,
[music]
each branch containing all the different
possible outcomes.
As physicist Bryce DeWitt eloquently put
it,
"Every quantum transition taking place
on every star in every galaxy and every
remote corner of the universe [music] is
splitting our local world on Earth into
myriads of copies."
In other words, if all possible states
of quantum particles exist, then all
physically possible outcomes of the
universe exist or will exist. We merely
only see the one we see because that is
the branch we have become entangled
with.
To us, everything appears continuous and
fixed, but in reality, it sort of isn't.
Instead, the universe comprises
infinitely or near infinitely many
parallel non-interacting worlds, each
branch on the quantum tree evolving
outward in its own direction.
Quantum [music] immortality.
What does this mean for each of our
lives and each of our [music] deaths? Of
course, it could mean nothing. It could
be wrong. But if we follow the current a
bit further, the idea of quantum
immortality suggests that if all
physically possible outcomes of the
universe exist or will exist, every
possible outcome of your life will as
well.
Where things get even stranger and more
unsettling, yet remain fully coherent
with the mathematics of quantum
mechanics, is that every possible
outcome of your life includes at least
one branch in which you or some version
of you survives everything.
Every near-death experience you've been
aware of but evaded,
every near-death experience you weren't
aware of but evaded, a car crash you
barely avoided, a disease you had that
didn't kill you. Every physically
possible cause of death you could have
died from but didn't. In each of these
moments, reality split and branched
outward on the quantum tree.
In certain branches, you died in each of
those moments.
But in this reality, containing this
version of you right now, you survived
all of them.
So far.
Perhaps in some upcoming moment, this
version of you right now might not be so
lucky. The particular branch you're
entangled with will bring you in front
of a car [music]
or under a storm or into an illness or
simply unto late age and a natural
death.
But according to the premise of quantum
immortality, some version of you will
continue [music] to be lucky.
Some version, like the version of you up
until this point, will continue to evade
every physically possible cause of
death,
including old age itself.
Some branches will contain medical
breakthroughs. Some will [music] have
different environmental conditions. Some
will have biological mutations or
technological augmentations. Some will
harbor incredibly improbable events.
And at least one will contain you riding
on the wave of these conditions forever.
>> [music]
>> Some semblance through line of your
subjective conscious experience that
continues to feel like you.
According to the philosopher David
Lewis, this version of you would
eventually find out the truth of the
many worlds interpretation, and your
improbable survivorship bias would be
the proof.
The unending illusion of the self.
Even if nothing is true about the many
worlds interpretation and quantum
immortality, what remains deeply
interesting and significant about the
ideas is what they bring up about the
very nature of the self.
We might reject the many worlds
interpretation and quantum immortality,
but we cannot reject the fact that in
every moment there is a kind of split
happening. A split between moments and
the self.
If you keep surviving, regardless of the
universe splitting, in this world right
now, you keep changing. You keep
departing from prior versions of
yourself and into [music] new present
ones, only for the new present ones to
quickly be departed from.
Across your lifetime, [music]
across each stage, each year, each week,
each day, each moment, a new version of
you emerges.
A clone based on what was clonable from
your prior [music] self.
Our bodies, our memories, our
preferences, our beliefs, and our values
are cloned from each moment into the
next.
But in each moment, things are [music]
different.
Each new moment is lived in a new world
with a new state of the body and mind.
Across time, the changing of the self
becomes increasingly perceivable.
Our bodies are different, made of
entirely [music] different cells.
Our preferences and values change. Our
memories become recontoured [music]
and amalgamate into new structures with
new memories and new vantage points. Our
external circumstances vary, evolve, and
erode. Altogether, very little, if not
nothing, remains consistent and stable.
Except some kind of continued sense of
subjective awareness.
Just like what is required and
considered in quantum immortality.
[music]
We continue to call this assemblage us,
me, I. And we perceive and feel it as if
it were fixed and continual.
But it isn't at all obvious if it
actually is.
What is this continued sense of
awareness?
If we return for a moment to the
question configured in the teleportation
[music] machine, that clone version of
you represents the same kind of split in
reality suggested in the many worlds
interpretation and suggested in the very
teleportive nature of time itself.
In every moment, an identical version of
you suddenly diverges into a new
separate reality,
>> [music]
>> into a separate condition.
But which one is you?
Is it always the same you? Is it never
the same you?
What are you?
If it's unclear in the teleportation
machine or in the many worlds
interpretation, then why is it clear
right now?
In the end, [music] quantum immortality
forces us to realize not only the
underlying uncertainty of everything we
are made of and exist through, but also
the uncertainties of who and what we are
philosophically.
It forces us to question if there ever
really could be a world in which you
exist at all.
Even if something like you might
continue on forever.
Whatever the self is, illusion or not,
immortal or not, there is, of course,
something here.
Something you experience as you.
Whether we live forever or die tomorrow.
[music]
To have been here at all, in any form,
on any branch on which we can sit and
ponder the night sky or the landscape
below,
is so unfathomably unlikely, perhaps it
can only mean one thing.
We are each proof of some kind of absurd
[music] improbability. Whatever it might
be.
Perhaps there is a through line of each
of our subjective conscious [music]
awareness currently on its way to
infinity.
Perhaps you are everywhere all the time
all at once.
But either way, right now you are here.
You are still alive.
You made it this far.
Only time in the universe
will tell how much farther
you will go.
While we're here in this branch of
[music] reality, we have to make the
most of it. This includes paying close
attention to the details of this life.
>> [music]
>> To the relationships we hold close. And
to taking the unique chances that this
version of us can. Pursuing our
interests relentlessly.
This video's sponsor, boot.dev, helps
you do just that
>> [music]
>> in a way that is meaningful and
effective.
In a world of increasing digital
opportunity, boot.dev makes keeping up
and learning coding in modern cloud
engineering [music]
enthralling and addictive. What I love
most about boot.dev is not only its vast
course offerings, but that it uses
modern game design to literally turn
learning into an RPG game. You go on
quests, fight bosses, earn XP, levels,
and achievements, all while building
skills that give you a huge competitive
advantage in the real [music] world. You
can learn Linux, AWS, Go, Docker, and
how to make AI work for you rather than
what is so often the other way around.
In today's world, boot.dev helps make
the difference between stagnating in
software or advancing ahead. All while
avoiding the tedium of tutorials or the
exorbitant expenses of traditional
education.
>> [music]
>> On boot.dev, all content is free to read
and watch, and a paid membership, which
is just 1% the price of traditional
education, unlocks all interactive
features and hands-on coding.
In the US in 2025, the median salary for
DevOps engineers or professionals was
$165,000.
So, the upside here is obvious,
>> [music]
>> and the risk is fun.
And since you stuck around, boot.dev is
offering you a special 30% off your
entire first year. That's an extra 5%
off compared to all those who didn't
make it this far in the video.
Just go to boot.dev and use code [music]
immortal.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.